done, I would strongly encourage people
not to believe what they read
in the mainstream media about how
well Ukraine is doing in this war
and how poorly Russia is doing,
The West is leading Ukraine
down the primrose path, and the Israelis
are executing a genocide in Gaza.
It's not China's fault
that it wants to be powerful.
So if you get into trouble
and you dial 911,
there's nobody at the other end.
Hi, this is John Mearsheimer.
And in today's episode, I'd like to talk
about the situation in Ukraine,
what's happening in the war
between Russia on one side and Ukraine
and the West on the other side.
I think if you read the newspapers
in the West every day
and you listen to the mainstream media
in the West, and this is certainly true
in Ukraine as well,
you get a picture
that the Russians are in real trouble.
They're struggling in this war.
The future looks bleak for the Russians.
And in contrast to the Russian situation,
the Ukrainians are actually doing
quite well, especially since they've
adopted drones on the battlefield.
And they're waging this long range
drone campaign.
And one has the sense that
at least we have a stalemate here.
And it may be the case
that the Ukrainians are turning the tide.
And when negotiations eventually start,
the Ukrainians will be
in a quite favorable position.
And of course, we're not talking
just about the Ukrainians.
We're talking about the Ukrainians
and the West,
because they are something of a tag team.
I disagree
almost completely with this view.
I've long argued, as many viewers know,
that the Russians would eventually win
and ugly victory.
And I think if you look at
what's actually happening in the war,
the Russians are winning the war
and the Ukrainians
are actually in terrible shape.
Again, I don't think you get this picture
from looking at
what's in the mainstream media
or listening to policymakers
in the West speak,
but I think they're wrong.
I think there's a propaganda campaign
at play here, and I want
to tell you a story that is at odds
with this propaganda campaign.
I want to tell you how
I think about the war, and I want to first
focus on the battlefield,
what's going on between
both sides, the Ukrainians
and the Russians on the battlefield
that I want to talk about the strategic
bombing campaign or the air war
that is being waged between the two sides.
Then I want to talk about the state
of outside support for Ukraine.
And here we're talking
about Western support for Ukraine,
what it looks like today
and where it might be headed.
Then I want to talk a bit about politics
or the political situation
inside of Ukraine itself.
And then I'll sum up by
talking about where the war is today
and where I think it's headed.
So let me start by first talking
about the battlefield.
And the key to keep in mind here
is that this is a war of attrition.
I don't think this is news to
anybody who's watching this video,
but I do think you want
to keep in mind that this war
is a slugfest.
This is a case of two armies standing
toe to toe on the battlefield.
And in a war of attrition.
What really matters more than
anything else is the balance of manpower,
or the balance of troops
that each side has,
and the balance of weaponry,
and in many ways that can be reduced
to the balance of firepower.
So let me talk
first about the balance of forces
or the balance of troops
up on the front lines.
I think that the Russians
at this point have a significant
advantage, which is hardly surprising
because the population differences
between the two sides is so great,
and because the troops are drawn
from the population of one side
has a much bigger population,
you would expect that side
to have more troops up on the front lines
than the other side.
And I would estimate that at this point,
the Russians have a population advantage
of roughly four and a half to one.
It's probably close to 5
to 1 at this point in time,
but that's really a massive advantage
for the Russians.
Just think about that.
Even if it's just 4 to 1, a 4
to 1 advantage in population size
favoring the Russians tells you
they're going to have
a lot more troops up on the front line
than the Ukrainians are.
And of course, that is the case.
We know that the Russians
have somewhere on the order of a
2 to 1 to 3 to 1 advantage
in front line troops.
And this problem for the Ukrainians
is exacerbated
by the fact
that they have a significant problem
with draft dodging,
and they have a significant problem
with AWOL, AWOL, or people
who run away from the battlefield.
They're soldiers who were sent up
to the battlefield to fight,
but at some point
they flee the battlefield.
And we know from listening
to the former minister of defense
in Ukraine speak
that Ukraine has a huge problem
with both AWOL and draft dodging.
So here you have an army
that's probably outnumbered,
probably close, close to 3 to 1
in terms of number of troops
that has inside it a significant AWOL
and draft dodging problem.
So the balance of forces favors
the Russians over the Ukrainians.
Moreover, when you talk about the balance
of forces up on the front lines,
you have to take into account the force
to space ratio.
In other words.
Do the Ukrainians have enough troops up
on the front lines
to thickly populate
the forward edge of the battle area,
or do they have a lack of troops,
which produces
a situation
where there are gaps in the front line?
Remember, there's a 1200 kilometer
front line that has to be covered,
and there is an abundance of evidence
coming from Ukrainian sources that the
Ukrainians do not have enough troops
to thickly populate the front lines.
And what's really saved them
in this situation has been drones.
Drones have been something of a stopgap.
In other words,
the Ukrainians can leave holes
in the front line
and then fill those lines with drones.
And then
if the
Russians do push through a particular gap,
they can move reserve troops
to close the gap.
But this is a significant problem
for the Russians.
So you see,
when you look at the number of troops up
on the front line, the Russians
significantly outnumber the Ukrainians.
And number two,
the Ukrainians do not have enough troops
to thickly populate the front lines.
Then we go to the matter of weaponry,
and here we're talking about firepower.
There's no question
that throughout the entire war,
the Russians have had a significant
advantage in artillery,
and nothing has changed in that regard.
And if anything, the Ukrainians
are having more difficulty than ever
getting artillery from the West,
and that includes the United States.
And one thing you want to remember about
Russia is that it has a very formidable
industrial base
that can produce huge numbers
of weapons on a monthly basis.
So there's no shortage of artillery
on the Russian side,
whereas there is a shortage of artillery
on the Ukrainian side.
And as I'm sure most of the viewers know,
throughout the course of this war
that has been talk about the Ukrainians
being outnumbered in terms of artillery,
sometimes 5 to 1, sometimes 7 to
1, and even sometimes 10 to 1.
Furthermore,
and this cannot be underestimated,
the Russians
have a huge inventory of glide bombs
that they have been launching
at the Ukrainian
forces on the ground
pretty much since the start of the war.
These
glide bombs are basically smart bombs.
They're old fashioned iron bombs
that have a special kick
put on them that allows
those bombs to land with precision
on the chosen target.
And estimates are that
the Russians have launched about 100,000
glide bombs against Ukrainian forces
since the war started,
and they're now averaging somewhere
in the range of 200
glide bombs
per day against Ukrainian forces.
So when you think about the balance
of firepower here,
you have to take into account or a tillery
and you have to take into account
these glide bombs.
And the Russians,
as I said, have a significant advantage
in terms of artillery
and in terms of glide bombs.
I just pointed out what an impressive
arsenal of glide bombs the Russians have.
At the same time, the Ukrainians
have hardly any glide bombs at all.
So the Russians have an overwhelming
advantage in terms of glide
bombs, a significant advantage
in terms of artillery.
The only way, the only place
where you have something of a balance
in terms of firepower up on
the front lines has to do with drones.
And there's no question
that both the Russians and Ukrainians
have a formidable force of drones
upon the front line.
And as I said before,
these drones have played a key role
in allowing the Ukrainians to compensate
for the fact
that they don't have enough troops
to cover the front line.
So drones have been a savior in a
very important way for the Ukrainians.
And I would argue
that in the absence of drones,
this war would have been over
a long time ago, because without drones,
both the balance of firepower
and the balance of manpower is so lopsided
in Russia's favor,
of course, that I think the
Russians would have rolled up
the Ukrainians a year or two ago.
But the fact is that
drones are ever present
on the front lines, and there you have
a rough balance of power.
Now, what about Russian casualties?
You hear all these stories in the news
about the astronomical Russian
casualty levels on the front lines.
And there are these stories
that have appeared
that say
that your average Russian conscript
will only live 20 to 30 hours
when he is sent to the front lines.
Just think about the argument
is that you take a Russian conscript,
you send them to the front lines
and he'll be dead somewhere
between 20 and 30 hours
after arriving at the front lines.
John Ratcliffe,
who is the head of the CIA,
has actually repeated this argument.
In this argument, of course, fuels
the claim that the Russians are suffering,
suffering massive casualties
on a daily basis, and well over
100,000 Russians have died or have been
severely wounded.
These numbers are ridiculous.
There's no question that the Russians have
suffered a few hundred thousand deaths.
I don't deny that for one second.
This is deadly combat, for sure.
But the idea that your average
Russian recruit
recruit only lasts somewhere between 20
to 30 hours is,
I think it's fair to say, ludicrous.
And in fact, if you look carefully
at how the Russians are waging the war,
they are waging it in a way
that is designed to minimize
the number of casualties.
This cannot be emphasized enough.
The Russians are moving very slowly
and very carefully,
and they are privileging firepower
over manpower in their assaults.
They want to do everything they can
to use firepower to eliminate
the Ukrainian forces before
they bring soldiers to bear in the fight.
And the reason here is
that the Russians are deeply interested
in not seeing their fighting forces die,
unless in large numbers.
I mean, you occasionally see reference
to the fact that Russian commanders force
their troops to engage in frontal attacks
where they get mowed down by
Ukrainian firepower.
There's
no evidence that this is happening.
The Russians are not engaging
in frontal attacks.
They're moving forward
in a very methodical way,
depending very heavily on firepower.
As I said before, to clear the way
for the attacking forces
and doing everything they can
to keep the number of casualties.
Damn.
On the other hand, it's quite clear
that the Ukrainians
are suffering significant casualties.
Budanov,
who is the head of or was formerly
the head of Ukrainian intelligence,
has recently said that the Ukrainians
need 30,000 new troops every month.
If the Ukrainians need 30,000 new troops
every month.
This implies that they're losing
30,000 troops every month.
Now, some of those troops
may have been lost by.
By desertion, by the troops going AWOL.
That's a serious possibility.
So let's say they're not losing
30,000 troops
in terms of casualties every month.
And when we talk about casualties
here, we're talking about
not we're not talking about people
who are lightly wounded.
We're talking about people
who were killed or severely wounded
and cannot come back into the fight.
So let's assume that the Ukrainians
are losing 25,000.
So we're modifying
number of 30,000.
And if
they're losing 25,000 troops a month,
they have to replace those 25,000,
25,000 over 12 months.
Is 300,000 troops.
That would mean that Ukraine,
according to its own
numbers, is losing 300,000 troops a year.
That is a huge number for an army
that is outnumbered to begin with.
So the point that I'm making to you
here, with regard
to Russian casualties
and Ukrainian casualties,
is that these claims about the numbers
that the Russians are
losing or wildly inflated,
and at the same time,
you do not want to lose sight
of the number of casualties
that the Ukrainians are suffering.
And of course, this is hardly surprising
when you take into account
that the balance of firepower,
when you look at things like artillery
and glide bombs, greatly favors
the Russians over the Ukrainians.
Now, one other issue
we want to talk about regarding
what's happening on the battlefield
is the fact that
the Russians are taking territory
very slowly.
Many people look at the slow pace
at which the Russians
are capturing territory, and they conclude
that this is evidence that the Russians
are failing to execute this war
in what one might call a satisfactory way.
I have a couple of points to make here.
First of all, one of the reasons
that the Russians are taking territory
very slowly is because they're moving
very cautiously, and they're moving
very cautiously and very deliberately
because they want to minimize casualties.
My point, my previous point
about minimizing casualties is linked
to this point about the speed at which
the Russians are taking territory.
There's no question
that they're taking territory very slowly.
And they're doing that again
because they want to minimize casualties.
Furthermore,
the Russians are fighting on terrain
where they have to go into large
towns and cities and capture
those cities, and to defeat the Ukrainians
in those large towns
and in those cities is a difficult task.
And it's a time consuming task.
And there's no way.
As the Russians move from east to west
in areas like the Donbass,
that they can take towns and cities
quickly, it's just not in the cards.
The Ukrainians are clearly fighting
fiercely in those cities,
and it takes time for the Russians
to capture territory.
But the point we want to keep in mind here
is that the Russians are slowly but
steadily capturing Ukrainian territory,
more and more Ukrainian territory.
And at the same time, and this is
very important in a war of attrition.
The Russians are killing
war, badly
wounding large numbers of Ukrainians,
and making it very difficult
for the Ukrainians to stay in the fight.
So I think when you put all these factors
together and you look at what's happening
on the front lines, there's no question
in my mind that the Russians
are winning on the battlefield,
that the Ukrainians are losing.
And given drones.
It has been difficult for the Russians
to knock out the Ukrainians.
There's no question about that.
But at the same time,
there is no question that the Ukrainians,
given the fact that they're outnumbered
in terms of troops
and that they're outnumbered
in terms of firepower,
that they are destined
to lose on the battlefield.
Now, let me switch gears
and talk about the air campaign.
And let me first
just talk about the inventory
of weaponry on both sides,
and then talk about the strategies
that both sides are employing
and how those strategies are likely
to affect the outcome of the war.
First of all,
let me talk about the Russian inventory.
The Russians have a huge inventory
of ballistic missiles and cruise missiles
that they have been using
against the Ukrainians.
Most estimates are
that the Russians have launched about 6000
ballistic missile and cruise
missile attacks against Ukraine,
in addition to the ballistic missiles
and the cruise missiles the Russians have.
As I said before, these glide bombs,
these smart bombs that they can launch
from the air and with pinpoint accuracy,
hit targets on the ground.
And as I said before, they've launched
100,000 glide bombs.
In addition,
the Russians are now getting assistance
from North Korean short
range ballistic missiles
because the North Koreans
are fighting side by side
with the Russians, and they are bringing
ballistic missiles with them.
And very importantly,
the Russians have a sophisticated
inventory of drones, jet powered drones.
The Geron four and the drone five are jet
powered drones
that are giving the Ukrainians fits.
If you look at the Ukrainian media,
if you look at the Kyiv Independent,
for example, it's
quite clear that the Russians
are having a powerful effect
in terms
of waging the air war against Ukraine
with all of these new jet powered drones
that the Ukrainians are having
a very difficult time shooting down.
And these drones
are not only difficult to shoot down,
but they are also very accurate
because they are steered to the target
by ground operators,
by Russian ground operators.
They're not just simply preprogramed
to go after a particular target
and then sent on their way.
On the contrary,
they're basically maneuvered to
their target by ground based operators,
and they fly at reasonably high altitudes.
They have the ability to maneuver, and
Ukrainians are having a devil of a time
dealing with this massive inventory
of jet powered drones
that the Russians have.
So when you look at
what the Russians have, you see again,
a huge inventory of ballistic
missiles, cruise
missiles,
glide bombs and jet powered drones.
And now they have North Korean ballistic
missiles at their disposal as well.
If you look at what the Ukrainians have,
as I said before,
they have virtually no glide bombs.
They have
virtually no ballistic missiles
of any consequence.
They do have some cruise missiles,
mainly cruise missiles
that they've gotten from the West.
These are the storm shadows
that they've gotten from the British,
but they have not gotten large numbers
of cruise missiles.
The number of cruise missiles that the
Ukrainians are firing at the Russians
pales in comparison to the number
of cruise missiles that the Russians
are firing at the Ukrainians.
And there's no reason
to think that's going to change
anytime soon.
And in terms of drones,
there's no question
that the Ukrainians
have a significant drone force.
This is a situation
that's analogous to the battlefield.
To go back to the battlefield.
Remember what I said?
I thought the drones had been Ukraine's
savior on the battlefield.
My argument was that without drones,
Ukraine would have lost
on the battlefield, in my opinion,
at least a year ago, maybe two years ago.
Drones have kept them in the fight.
And in terms of the inventory of strategic
air assets, I think drones are where the
where the Ukrainians have
been, by and large, able
to match the Russians.
They don't have a sophisticated force
of jet powered drones.
That's the equivalent of what
the Russians have.
But nevertheless, there's no question
that the Ukrainians have
a powerful force of drones.
That they have been using.
But otherwise,
if you move away from drones,
you look at all these other weapons.
The Russians have
a decisive advantage
in the number of cruise missiles,
ballistic missiles,
glide bombs and so forth and so on.
So that's the basic inventory.
But what's more important
than the inventory, or at least
as important than the inventory,
is the question of sort of how you employ
those air assets
to affect the outcome of the war.
And I think you can talk about an air
campaign in two different ways.
First, you can envision
an air campaign as a punishment campaign.
And with a punishment campaign,
you end up killing lots of people
or wrecking the other side's economy
or damaging the other side's
economies in ways that cause great
pain for the population and force.
You force the population to put pressure
on the government to end the war.
So the idea is that if you
hit a city
and you take out the energy network
in that city and people don't have water
or they don't have heating,
people will rise up and put pressure
on the government to end the war.
Or the government itself will say,
enough is enough.
So much
pain is being inflicted on our population.
So much punishment
is being inflicted on our population
that this war has to be ended.
That's one way
you can think about employing air power.
Second way you can think about employing
air power is you tear apart
military infrastructure in the rear
areas of your adversary,
and you wreck the other side's
economy in ways
that affect its ability
to wage war up on the front lines.
So you're not in this second
with this second strategy.
You're not punishing
the civilian population.
You're not causing the civilian population
to rise up against the government
or causing the government to say
enough is enough
because the civilian population
is being so badly hurt.
No, the second strategy calls
for doing great damage to the economy
and to military infrastructure
in ways that influences
the fighting between the two sides.
Now, I think up until recently,
the Russian campaign
really focused on the first strategy.
It was really,
by and large, a punishment campaign.
And I think
if you look at what Ukraine is doing,
Ukraine strategy has been
and still is a punishment campaign.
And when we talk about Ukraine's air
campaign here, we're talking about it's
it's drone campaign, right.
Basically a punishment strategy.
And as I say, I think the Russians
have been waging a punishment
strategy up until recently as well.
Punishment strategies just don't work.
Just look at the damage
that Russia has done
with its air war against Ukraine
over the past few years, and there is zero
evidence that it has caused Ukraine
to think about quitting the war.
And the same thing is true when you look
at Ukraine's drone campaign,
this is its long range drone campaign
against the Russian heartland.
There's no way that's
going to cause Russia to quit the war.
Punishment campaigns don't work,
and the Ukrainian punishment
campaign against
Russia is a much less potent
punishment campaign
than the Russian campaign against Ukraine.
And again, the Russian punishment campaign
did not get Ukraine to quit.
But what's happened here?
What's changed in the Russian campaign,
the Russian strategic bombing campaign,
is that it has gone from a punishment
campaign to a campaign
that's designed to wreck
the Ukrainian economy in ways
that will significantly influence
events on the battlefield.
And that bombing campaign is also
now directed at influencing
actual military events
by going after targets
in the rear areas of Ukraine
that contain military infrastructure.
Now, what exactly am I talking about here
in recent months?
What Russia has done it is
that is turned Ukraine
into a landlocked country.
The importance of this
cannot be underestimated
because Ukraine depends
heavily on its Black Sea ports
to export and import
agricultural goods, industrial goods
and military
wherewithal, military wherewithal.
You want to think about that?
So what's happened here is that
Russia has concentrated on shutting down
ports like Odesa
and other ports along the Black Sea.
These are Ukrainian ports,
which is which has made it
virtually impossible
for Ukraine to import and export
goods, be
they military or economic, at those ports.
And this is why I said that
what's happened here is Russia has turned
Ukraine into a landlocked country.
This is having devastating effects
on the Ukrainian economy.
There's no way that
that could not be the case.
And we know from back in 2022,
when those ports were shut down
for a number of months that it had
then it then had devastating effects
on the Ukrainian economy.
So there's no question
that given that the Russians
have shut down
those Black Sea ports, turned Ukraine
into a landlocked country,
that this is going to go to great lengths.
This will go to great lengths to damage
severely the Ukrainian economy.
And this matters
because the Ukrainian economy
healthy or a reasonably healthy
Ukrainian economy or functioning
Ukrainian economy, is essential
for supporting
the troops on the front line.
On top of the damage that's being done
to the Ukrainian economy,
the fact is that lots of Russian,
lots of excuse, excuse me,
lots of Ukrainian military material
came in through the Black Sea ports
and that is no longer the case.
So weaponry, precious weaponry
that was coming in through those
Ukrainian ports on the Black Sea
are no longer coming in.
And this too is having having an effect
on the battlefield.
Furthermore, if you look at
what the Russians
are doing to the transportation network
inside of Russia,
they are wrecking railroad lines.
They are attacking locomotives,
they're destroying
gas stations in droves in eastern Ukraine.
They're tearing apart road networks
and and rail lines as well.
And the end result of
this is the transportation
network
inside of Ukraine is being badly damaged,
which not only hurts the economy
but makes it very difficult
to move material from the rear
areas to the front line forces.
It's quite clear that if
you look at retail, warehouse,
storage, retail, warehouse, storage
inside of Ukraine,
that estimates from high level
government officials are
that the Russians have destroyed 90%
of retail warehouse storage,
which has a significant effect
on the Russian economy.
And the Russians up to now
have either damaged
or destroyed about 80% of Ukraine's
energy infrastructure.
Just think about the Russians up to now
have destroyed about 80% of destroyed
or damaged about 80% of Ukraine's energy
infrastructure.
A lot of that has been repaired.
I want to be clear, but what the Russians
are now saying that they're going to do
is they're going to destroy that
energy infrastructure almost completely.
They're going to purposely target that
infrastructure, that energy infrastructure
for the purpose of with the goal
in mind of destroying it.
So you can see what's happening here.
And that is that the Russians are no
longer engaged in a punishment campaign.
They're interested in wrecking
the Ukrainian economy to the point
where it will
greatly hinder Ukraine's ability
to support the front line forces.
And in addition, they're going
after military infrastructure.
They're going after military targets
in Ukraine's rear, which,
of course, will eventually weaken
Ukraine's efforts on the front lines.
So what I am saying here
is that when you look at
what Russia is doing up on the front
lines, the successes
that it's having up on the battlefield,
and you couple that with the change
that has recently taken place
and the strategy
it is employing in the air war,
it's quite clear that the Russians are
at a significant advantage or have a
significant advantage over the Ukrainians.
Now, just one final point on this,
and that is that if you look
at the Ukrainian air campaign
against Russia, which is being waged
with drones, there's no question
that that is inflicting
punishment on Russia.
We want to be very clear on that point.
The Ukrainian drone campaign is inflicting
punishment on Russia,
but that punishment campaign
is not going to cause Russia to surrender
or to reduce its goals in this war.
If anything, it's going to incentivize
the Russians to take more territory
and to ramp up its own
air campaign against Ukraine
to the highest possible level.
So the Ukrainians have no war
winning strategy
when it comes to the air war.
And when you read all these stories
about how successful
this drone attack or that drone attack
by Ukraine against Russia is,
you should understand
it's not going to influence the outcome
of this war in any meaningful way.
So that concludes my discussion
of the military side of the war.
I want to talk now about outside support
for Ukraine,
as I think everybody understands Ukraine
could have never stayed in this war
without support from the West,
especially from the United States.
And if you think about where we are today
and where we're headed, it's quite clear
that US support for
Ukraine has been reduced
significantly
since the war started in February 2022.
The United States, under President Trump,
has made it clear that what
the white House wants to do is reduce
the American burden of supporting
Ukraine and shift
that burden onto the shoulders
of the Europeans.
So the United States is interested
in reducing its commitment to Ukraine
to take this further.
Remember that the United States,
because of what's happened in the Gulf
War, has a significant shortage
of precious munitions.
For example, it has a significant shortage
of Patriot missiles.
The Ukrainians are desperate
to get American Patriot missiles.
They need Patriot missiles to help defend
against the ballistic missiles
and cruise missiles
that the Russians are now firing
at Ukraine in huge numbers.
But the United States has no Patriot
missiles
that it can give to the Ukrainians.
The Ukrainians,
therefore, have virtually no defense
against the incoming
ballistic and cruise missiles from Russia.
And that situation is not going to change
anytime soon.
The United States is not in a position
where it can give lots of weaponry to
Ukraine.
And furthermore, the United States, as I
said, is interested in shifting the burden
of supporting Ukraine from its shoulders
to the European shoulders.
On top of all that, the United States
has just initiated the study
to assess what sort of troop levels
the United States should maintain
in Europe moving forward,
and given the imperative
of pivoting to Asia and giving
what's going on in the Middle East,
it's almost certain that the United States
is going to reduce
its troop levels in
Europe in the not too distant future,
and this is just going to be another sign
of America's
reduced commitment to Ukraine.
So you see, you have a situation here
where the American commitment to Europe,
I don't want to say
it's been withering away.
That's too strong,
but it has been greatly reduced over time.
It hasn't been reduced to zero.
But the United States is no longer
the loyal supporter of Ukraine
that it once was.
And if you look at the European countries,
relations
between Poland and Ukraine have badly
deteriorated.
The polls have made it clear
they will not fight in Ukraine
under almost any circumstances.
There's a lot of bad blood these days
between Poland
and Ukraine,
because Ukraine has been supporting
or has been celebrating
its history in World War two,
in which Ukrainian forces massacred poles,
which has enraged poles
and therefore Polish.
Ukrainian relations are terrible today.
And if you look at what's happening inside
in France and Germany, it is possible
that the right will win in both France
and Germany in a future election.
And if the right wins
in one of those elections,
it's likely that France or Germany
will abandon its strong support
for Ukraine, because the right in Germany
and the right in France have made it clear
that they have no love lost for NATO.
Number one.
And number two,
they think it's time to end this
formidable be a German or be
it French commitment to Ukraine.
So when you look at the future
and you think about Ukraine's
heavy dependance
on support from the United States
and from the Europeans,
you don't see a pretty picture at all.
And then I want to talk about
what's going on inside of Ukraine.
First of all, there's a lot of war
weariness.
Recent polls show that 66% of Ukrainians
think it's time to
negotiate an end to the war.
Only 24%.
This is roughly one out of every four
Ukrainians wants to continue this war.
Furthermore, if you look at Zelensky's
standing inside of Ukraine,
there's no question
that he still garners
significant political support.
It's not like the body
populist wants to throw him out of office,
but it's quite clear that
if you were to have an election today,
it is likely that 2 or 3
other Ukrainians would defeat him
because he is not the most popular leader
anymore.
In Ukraine, there are others, like Budanov
who I was talking about
before his former defense minister
Fedorov and his former
commanding general, General Zaluzhnyi
All of whom are more popular
than Zelensky.
So Zelensky has some political problems
on the home front.
And then the final point I'd make about
what's going on regarding Ukraine's home
front is that Zelensky was recently forced
into a position
where he had to fire
both the minister of defense.
This is Fedorov,
who is
now interested in having an election
because he thinks he could beat
Zelensky in an election. But
he was not only forced to fire Fedorov,
he was forced to fire General Syrskyi as well.
And I believe the general Syrskyi was
a quite successful battlefield commander.
I think one of the reasons,
not the only reason by any means,
but one of the reasons that the Ukrainians
have been able to hold out
against the Russians over
time was because of General Syrskyi
who was, I think,
a quite competent military commander.
But anyway, so
Zelensky has been forced to fire Syrskyi.
He was forced to fire Fedorov.
And when you were in the middle
of a tough war
and you have to simultaneously fire
your Minister of defense
and the commanding general of your armed
forces,
that tells you
that you are in serious trouble.
So the point that I'm making here
is that if you look inside
Kyiv,
there's all sorts of trouble brewing.
And if you look at the outside support
for Kyiv, there's all sorts of trouble
brewing there.
And then when you marry that
to what's happening on the battlefield
and what's happening in the strategic
bombing campaigns.
This is a very bleak picture.
Now, where
exactly is the war today?
The Russians have a next for oblast
plus Crimea.
They've annexed somewhere
on the order of 20
plus percent of Ukrainian territory.
Of course,
they don't control all of that territory,
but I would estimate they control
slightly
more than 80% of those four oblasts.
They control all of Crimea and about 80%
of the four oblasts that they inex.
And there are,
of course, in the process of conquering
all of the territory
in those four oblasts.
So if the war ended today,
Ukraine would have lost
about 20% of its territory.
Not only has Ukraine
lost all this territory,
but there's virtually no chance
it's going to become a member of NATO.
First of all, NATO is a badly damaged
institution as a result of this war.
Serious damage has been done to NATO
because of the Ukraine war.
And you see this very clearly in America's
interest
in reducing its presence in Europe,
reducing its influence in NATO,
and basically letting the Europeans play
a much larger role
in terms of running the alliance.
So I think the alliance is in trouble.
But furthermore,
there's no way you're going to get
a European consensus
to bring Ukraine into NATO.
And furthermore, given
the state of Ukraine, given the damage
that's been done to Ukraine,
Ukraine will be in no position
to enter NATO or the EU for that matter.
So again, you end the war today.
Russia controls a huge slice
of Ukrainian territory in the East,
and furthermore,
it has succeeded in preventing
Ukraine from join in NATO.
Finally,
huge destruction has been done to Ukraine.
Estimates
are that it'll take $600 billion.
Just think about that.
$600 billion to repair
all the damage
that has been done to Ukraine.
And this doesn't take out take
into account the demographic consequences.
All the people who have fled Ukraine
and will never come back.
All the Ukrainians who have died before
this war started, it was commonplace
for people to talk about Ukraine
being a demographic death spiral.
If anything, that situation
has only been exacerbated.
So in terms of where we are today
and the war,
were that war to end today.
I think it's quite clear that Ukraine
is in a disastrous situation,
and I think there is no chance
that Ukraine can reverse this situation.
Anybody who believes that
Ukraine can recapture
territory that it lost, that it can wage
a strategic bombing campaign
that can bring the Russians to their knees
and get them to negotiate an agreement,
get the Russians to negotiate an agreement
that is favorable to Ukraine, and reverse
as much of the damage
that has been
done is living in a dream world.
This is just not going to happen.
The best that the Ukrainians can hope for
at this point in
time is freezing the status quo.
And as I say,
if you freeze the status quo.
This is a disastrous outcome for Ukraine.
It's a dysfunctional rump state.
It's lost at least 20% of its territory.
It's suffered
enormous physical destruction.
Large
numbers of people have left the country.
Huge numbers of people have died.
This is a disaster.
But the real problem is that
this war is not over.
With that the Russians are on the march.
I do not deny for one second
that the Russians are moving slowly.
But when you look at the strategic
bombing campaign and the damage
that's being done to Ukraine,
and you take into account
the fact that Russia is capturing
territory on the front lines
and it is killing more
and more Ukrainians.
Again,
you want to remember that General Budanov
says that
Ukraine needs 30,000 new men each month.
You understand that as bleak
as the situation is now,
it only gets worse
with the passage of time.
So when all is said and done,
I would strongly encourage people
not to believe what they read
in the mainstream media about how
well Ukraine is doing in this war
and how poorly Russia is doing,
because I think if anything, exactly
the opposite is happening.
Thank you very much for listening to this
video,
and I look forward to our next
episode together.
Thank you.